<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Matthew L. Jones</title>
    <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org" />
    <updated>2023-12-06T23:00:59-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.nescioquid.org</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Steering Machine Learning into Artificial Intelligence</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/steering-machine-learning-into-artificial-intelligence.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/steering-machine-learning-into-artificial-intelligence.html</id>

        <updated>2023-03-16T16:30:46-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    What funding arrangements and organizations propelled the field of machine learning, now rebranded artificial intelligence, to its centrality today? How did these diverse funders and practitioners shape protocols for reward and promotion of diverse research values? How did the relationship of corporate, non-profit, and governmental&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                
  <p>
    What funding arrangements and organizations propelled the field of machine learning, now rebranded artificial intelligence, to its centrality today? How did these diverse funders and practitioners shape protocols for reward and promotion of diverse research values? How did the relationship of corporate, non-profit, and governmental funding shift from the 1970s to the present? How—and why—has the field remained strongly committed to academic and open-source values while simultaneously dominated by enormous corporate funding—indeed, by corporations capable of hiring entire academic departments? How are narratives about the current success, if not domination, of machine learning being used to legitimate changes in the organization and mandates of funding for other sciences and engineering activities?
  </p>

  <p>
    This project aims to begin empirically answering these questions through the examination of corporate, academic, foundation, and governmental archives, both civilian and military. Alongside tracking flows of funds and explicit priorities of funders, the project will chart the movement of protocols of publication and publicity between academia and the corporate world, continuities and disruptions around intellectual property and trade secrets, and challenges around access to data, code, computer resources, and finally the sociologies of science and engineering implicitly and explicitly built into processes of funding and continuing support.&nbsp;<br>
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Data Happened</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/how-data-happened.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/how-data-happened.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/9/HOW-DATA-HAPPENED_website-banner.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-12-06T23:00:59-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/9/HOW-DATA-HAPPENED_website-banner.png" alt="" />
                    A sweeping history of data and its technical, political, and ethical impact on our world.&nbsp; Co-authored with Chris Wiggins, Columbia and Chief Data Scientist, NY Times&nbsp; "fascinating" — Jill Lepore, The New Yorker Top Books of 2023—The New Yorker Top 10 Science Books of Spring&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/9/HOW-DATA-HAPPENED_website-banner.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                
  <p class="align-center">
    A sweeping history of data and its technical, political, and ethical impact on our world.&nbsp; Co-authored with Chris Wiggins, Columbia and Chief Data Scientist, NY Times&nbsp;
  </p>

  <p class="align-center">
    "fascinating" — Jill Lepore, <i>The New Yorker</i>
  </p>

  <p class="align-center">
    Top Books of 2023—<i>The New Yorker</i>
  </p>

  <p class="align-center">
    Top 10 Science Books of Spring 2023—Publishers Weekly
  </p>
<div><p align="center">
<a href="https://www.bookculture.com/book/9781324006732">Book Culture</a>  
<a href="https://www.indiebound.org/book/9781324006732">Indiebound</a>   
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/How-Data-Happened-History-Algorithms/dp/1324006730/">Amazon</a>  <a href="https://www.barnesandnoble.com/w/how-data-happened-chris-wiggins/1141651636">Barnes & Noble</a>
</p>

</div>

  <p>
    
  </p>

  <p>
    "Trenchant and successfully illuminates the contingency of data’s privileged place in modern decision-making. Incisive and thoroughly researched, this one's a winner." —Publishers Weekly<br>
  </p>

  <p>
    "This is the first comprehensive look at the history of data and how power has played a critical role in shaping the history. It’s a must read for any data scientist about how we got here and what we need to do to ensure that data works for everyone." —DJ Patil, former U.S. Chief Data Scientist<br>
  </p>

  <p>
    "In a tour de force, Wiggins and Jones put data in context so that we can see the values, politics, and controversies that shape our present reality. This book is truly a semester-long class bottled into a narrative fit for vacation." —danah boyd<br><br>    "Sometimes the best way to understand the present and prepare for the future is to look to the past. This insight is at the core of <i>How Data Happened</i>, an ambitious and thoughtful work … that will reshape how you will see the relationship between data and society." —Matthew J. Salganik<br><br>    "Ambitious and bold.… A must-read for everyone interested in how data is changing our lives." —Gina Neff<br><br>    "An essential, authoritative history of the increasing power of data, how new capabilities have transformed society, and what we must do to ensure that today’s technology reflects our norms and values." —Renee DiResta<br><br>"An informative dive into the history of statistics and data, providing context for the debate over information and who controls it." —Kirkus Reviews<br><br>
  </p>

  <p>
    Forthcoming in&nbsp; Brazilian Portuguese (Alta Books), Korean (CMass21 Publishing Co.); Simplified Mandarin (Ginkgo Book Co.); Traditional Mandarin (The Commercial Press); Turkish (Serenad Publishing), Polish (Helion)
  </p>

  <p>
    
  </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Collaboration</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/collaboration.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/collaboration.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/radio-nets.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-06-21T10:27:36-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/radio-nets.jpg" alt="" />
                    CIFAR Future Flourishing What does it mean to live (well) without human exceptionalism? The idea that humans are separate from their environment, other organisms, or the tools they use — human exceptionalism — has been critiqued from all sides. But what will it mean to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/radio-nets.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <div><p><a href="https://cifar.ca/research-programs/future-flourishing/"> CIFAR Future Flourishing</a></p>
<img loading="lazy" src="https://cifar.ca/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Future-Flourishing_webanner-1920x400.jpg" data-is-external-image="true">
<p>
What does it mean to live (well) without human exceptionalism?

The idea that humans are separate from their environment, other organisms, or the tools they use — human exceptionalism — has been critiqued from all sides. But what will it mean to flourish without exceptionalism in the future? The interdisciplinary network in the Future Flourishing program brings together philosophers, historians, curators, conservators, artists and anthropologists to imagine what it will take to create a better world for all of the entities that make up humans and live with us.

The questions the Future Flourishing program will ask are more than purely intellectual, they should have real impact on the kind of society we want to create at different levels, political, scientific, and moral. We are reacting to, and coping with, a multiplicity of crises. We start from the claim that such crises are, in part, the product of the fiction of human exceptionalism, that is, of the rational individual mind cut off from his or her environment that we have inherited from the moderns. In this program, we seek to understand the implications (good and bad) that the notion of human exceptionalism has had and still has on the kind of knowledge associated (perhaps too easily) with “the West.” We will expand this research question in new directions, based in three “pillars” of work. Central to this work is a concerted inquiry into and recovery of the uses of exceptionalism both within and beyond conventional definitions of the modern and its histories (Pillar 1). A second goal will be to explore the concrete (good and bad) effects of the modern fable of human exceptionalism, and the diverse, persistent alternatives that preceded and accompanied it (Pillar 2). All this will focus our efforts to integrate these ideas (or enter into dialogue with them) in the creation of our own fiction (Pillar 3).

2023-2028</div>

  <div  class="gallery-wrapper gallery-wrapper--wide">
    <div class="gallery" data-columns="3">
      <figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/gallery/Screenshot-2023-01-24-at-8.26.49-PM.png" data-size="1220x2042">
        <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/gallery/Screenshot-2023-01-24-at-8.26.49-PM-thumbnail.png" height="1205" width="720" alt="" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>Histories of AI: A Genealogy of Power (Mellon-Sawyer)</figcaption>
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/gallery/1105208293172174848-D1Z81OTX4AE-Hbt.jpg" data-size="740x552">
        <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/gallery/1105208293172174848-D1Z81OTX4AE-Hbt-thumbnail.jpg" height="537" width="720" alt="" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>toward a history of artificial intelligence (Columbia Workshop</figcaption>
    </figure>
    </div>
  </div>

  <div  class="gallery-wrapper">
    <div class="gallery" data-columns="1">
      <figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/gallery/Screenshot-2023-01-24-at-9.06.55-PM.png" data-size="1008x1086">
        <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/8/gallery/Screenshot-2023-01-24-at-9.06.55-PM-thumbnail.png" height="776" width="720" alt="" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>Data: Past, Present, & Future</figcaption>
    </figure>
    </div>
  </div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Books</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/books.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/books.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/Image00059-Large.jpeg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-06-04T10:58:20-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/Image00059-Large.jpeg" alt="" />
                    The Good Life in the Scientific Revolution: Descartes, Pascal, Leibniz and the Cultivation of Virtue (University of Chicago Press, 2006). Reckoning with Matter: Calculating, Innovation, and Thinking about Thinking from Pascal to Babbage (University of Chicago Press, 2016). How Data Happened (Norton, 2023) (with Chris&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/Image00059-Large.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                
  <p>
    
  </p>

  <div  class="gallery-wrapper gallery-wrapper--wide">
    <div class="gallery" data-columns="3">
      <figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/gallery/GLSR_cover.jpg" data-size="432x645">
        <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/gallery/GLSR_cover-thumbnail.jpg" height="645" width="432" alt="" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>Good Life in the Scientific Revolution</figcaption>
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/gallery/Reckoning_cover.jpg" data-size="860x1298">
        <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/gallery/Reckoning_cover-thumbnail.jpg" height="1087" width="720" alt="" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>Reckoning With Matter</figcaption>
    </figure><figure class="gallery__item">
      <a href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/gallery/howdatahappenedcover.jpg" data-size="1877x2788">
        <img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/7/gallery/howdatahappenedcover-thumbnail.jpg" height="1069" width="720" alt="" >
      </a>
      <figcaption>How Data Happened</figcaption>
    </figure>
    </div>
  </div>
<div><p><a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/G/bo3793367.html"><em>The Good Life in the Scientific Revolution: Descartes, Pascal, Leibniz and the Cultivation of Virtue</em> (University of Chicago Press, 2006).</a></p>
<p><a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/R/bo24836963.html"></em>Reckoning with Matter: Calculating, Innovation, and Thinking about Thinking from Pascal to Babbage (University of Chicago Press, 2016).</a></p>
<p><em><a href="https://wwnorton.com/books/how-data-happened">How Data Happened</a></em> (Norton, 2023) (with <a href="http://datascience.columbia.edu/chris-h-wiggins">Chris Wiggins</a>).</p>

</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>About</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/contacts.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/contacts.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/RR_12333.jpg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-09-12T09:27:27-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/RR_12333.jpg" alt="" />
                    Matthew L. Jones is the Smith Family Professor of History at Princeton University. In 2023, Norton published his How Data Happened: A History from the Age of Reason to the Age of Algorithms, written with Chris Wiggins. He is completing a book, Great Exploitations on&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/RR_12333.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><strong>Matthew L. Jones</strong> is the Smith Family Professor of History at Princeton University. In 2023, Norton published his <em>How Data Happened: A History from the Age of Reason to the Age of Algorithms</em>, written with Chris Wiggins. He is completing a book, <em>Great Exploitations</em> on state surveillance of communications and information warfare. He has published two books previously, <em>Reckoning with Matter: Calculating Machines, Innovation, and Thinking about Thinking from Pascal to Babbage</em> and <em>The Good Life in the Scientific Revolution: Descartes, Pascal, Leibniz and the Cultivation of Virtue</em> (both with Chicago). The Mellon Foundation, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, the Guggenheim Foundation, and the National Science Foundation have funded his research and teaching.</p>
<p><a rel="me" href="https://mastodon.social/@nescioquid">mastodon.social</a></p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nescioquid">twitter</a></p>
<p><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/nescioquid.bsky.social">bluesky</a></p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/matthewljones">Github</a></p>
<p><a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6163-9401">Orcid</a></p>
<h4 id="address">Address</h4>
<p><a href="https://history.princeton.edu">Department of History</a></p>
<p>Princeton University</p>
<p>129 Dickinson Hall</p>
<p>Princeton, NJ 08544-1017</p>
<p><a href="emailto:mljones@princeton.edu">Princeton email</a></p>
<p><a href="mailto:mjones@nescioquid.org">Email</a></p>
<p><figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/Jones_headshot.jpg" alt="Headshot" width="378" height="504"  sizes="100vw" srcset="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/responsive/Jones_headshot-xs.jpg 300w ,https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/responsive/Jones_headshot-sm.jpg 480w ,https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/responsive/Jones_headshot-md.jpg 768w ,https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/responsive/Jones_headshot-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/responsive/Jones_headshot-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/6/responsive/Jones_headshot-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></p>
<p>Photo credit: Elizabeth H. Lee</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Papers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/papers.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/papers.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/5/1318762317421608962-Ek0vLeWWMAIaX8n-2.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-09-12T09:29:23-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/5/1318762317421608962-Ek0vLeWWMAIaX8n-2.png" alt="" />
                    “Social experts within and without: social epistemologies and the Netflix competition in the making of machine learning,” Social Studies of Science (under review). [“Users gone astray: spreadsheet charts, junky graphics and statistical knowledge,”] (https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/725133) Osiris 38(2023):185-204. “Artificial Intelligence in History / History of Artificial Intelligence,”&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/5/1318762317421608962-Ek0vLeWWMAIaX8n-2.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>“Social experts within and without: social epistemologies and the Netflix competition in the making of machine learning,” <em>Social Studies of Science</em> (under review).</p>
<p>[“Users gone astray: spreadsheet charts, junky graphics and statistical knowledge,”] (<a href="https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/725133">https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/10.1086/725133</a>) <em>Osiris</em> 38(2023):185-204. </p>
<p>“Artificial Intelligence in History / History of Artificial Intelligence,” for roundtable on AI and history, American Historical Review (forthcoming). </p>
<p>“Decision trees, random forests, and the genealogy of the black box,” <em>Algorithmic Modernity: Mechanizing Thought and Action, 1500-2000</em>, Massimo Mazzotti and Morgan Ames, ed. (Oxford, 2023), 190-215.</p>
<p>“Programming,” in <em>Information: A Historical Companion.</em> Ann Blair, Paul Duguid, Anja Goeing, Anthony Grafton, eds. (Princeton University Press, 2020), 703-708.</p>
<p>“Creating Uncertainty, Casting Doubt: US Intelligence Leaks from Intelligence Reform to Spyware for Sale,” in <em>Exposing Secrets: The Forgotten History of U.S. National Security Whistleblowing and the Challenge of Dissent</em>, Kaetan Mistry and Hannah Gurman, eds. (Columbia University Press, 2019), 243-270.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~mj340/HSNS4805_12_Jones.pdf">“How We Became Instrumentalists (Again): Data Positivism since World War II.”</a> <em>Historical Studies in the Natural Sciences</em> 48, no. 5 (November 1, 2018): 673–84.</p>
<p><a href="http://limn.it/the-spy-who-pwned-me/">The spy who pwned me</a><em>, Limn</em>, edd. Chris Kelty and Biella Coleman, Issue 8.</p>
<p>“Calculating Machine” in Maria-Rosa Antognazza, ed. <em>Oxford Handbook of Leibniz</em> (Oxford, 2018).</p>
<p>“Calculating Devices and Computers,” <em>Companion to the History of Science</em>, ed. Bernie Lightman (Wiley, 2016). <a href="Jones_calc_comp_preprint.pdf">Preprint</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.columbia.edu/~mj340/jones_2017_querying.pdf">“Querying the Archive: Database Mining from Apriori to Page-Rank,”</a><a href="http://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/S/bo25231630.html"><em>Science in the Archive</em></a>, Lorraine Daston, ed. (University of Chicago Press, 2017). <a href="Jones_archives_preprint.pdf">Preprint</a></p>
<p>“Data and Hubris” in Rachel Schutt and Cathy O’Neill, eds. <em>Doing Data Science</em> (O’Reilly, 2014).</p>
<p>“Reason, Calculating Machines and Efficient Causation” in Tad Schmaltz, ed. <em>Efficient Causation: The History of a Concept</em> (Oxford, 2014).</p>
<p>“Space, Evidence, and the Authority of Mathematics in the Eighteenth Century” in Aaron Garrett, ed. <em>Routledge Companion to Eighteenth-Century Philosophy</em> (Routledge, 2014).</p>
<p>“Improvement for Profit: Calculating Machines and the Prehistory of Intellectual Property,” Mario Biagioli and Jessica Riskin, eds., <em>Nature Engaged: Science in Practice from the Renaissance to the Present</em> (Palgrave-MacMillan, 2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/rapidpdf/333/6048/1382?ijkey=mfrgKdepAV7Sk&keytype=ref&siteid=sci">“d(scientist)/dt,”</a> <em>Science</em> 333(2011):1382-3. (Review of Peter Harrison, Ronald Numbers and Michael H. Shank, eds. <em>Wrestling with Nature: From Omens to Science</em> [Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2011]).</p>
<p><a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11016-011-9597-2">Essay review</a> of Lorraine Daston and Peter Galison, <em>Objectivity,</em> (2007), <em>Metascience</em>, 21 (2012).</p>
<p><a href="http://www.h-france.net/vol11reviews/vol11no229Jones.pdf">Essay review</a> of Emilie Du Châtelet, <em>Selected Philosophical and Scientific Writings.</em> Bour and Zinsser, trans. (2009) <em>H-France</em> 11(2011), No. 229.</p>
<p><a href="http://journals.cambridge.org/repo_A79TfSIV">“Matters of Fact”</a> [Essay review of Harold Cook, <em>Matters of Exchange</em> (Yale 2007)] <em>Modern Intellectual History</em> 7,3 (2010): 629-642.</p>
<p>“Three Errors about Indifference: Pascal on the Vacuum, Sociability and Moral Freedom,” <em>Romance Quarterly</em> 50(2003):99-120.</p>
<p>“Writing and <em>Sentiment</em>: Blaise Pascal, the Vacuum and the <em>Pensées,</em>”  <em>Studies in History and Philosophy of Science</em>, 32(2001):139-181.</p>
<p>“Descartes’ Geometry as Spiritual Exercise,” <em>Critical Inquiry</em>, 28(2001): 40-71; reprinted in Bill Brown, ed. <em>Things</em>. (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2004): 40-71.</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Media</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/media.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/media.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/4/Ada-Lovelace-lectures-to-crowd-about-difference-engine-in-style-of-Cowboy-bebop.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-01-24T23:33:42-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/4/Ada-Lovelace-lectures-to-crowd-about-difference-engine-in-style-of-Cowboy-bebop.png" alt="" />
                    lectures Great Exploitations: Data Mining, Legal Modernization, and the NSA (UC Berkeley) A Brief History of Surveillance State Technology Pitt’s Information Ecosystems Podcast with Sarah Conell “The Ethics of Big Data,” Future Hindsight with Mila Atmos
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/4/Ada-Lovelace-lectures-to-crowd-about-difference-engine-in-style-of-Cowboy-bebop.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2 id="lectures">lectures</h2>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/Qx4Wupf1okc">Great Exploitations: Data Mining, Legal Modernization, and the NSA (UC Berkeley)</a></p>
<p><a href="http://livestream.com/internetsociety/F2C2015/videos/79063537">A Brief History of Surveillance State Technology</a></p>
<h2 id="interviews">interviews</h2>
<p>Pitt’s <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/episode-2-matthew-jones/id1488946417?i=1000458864363">Information Ecosystems Podcast</a> with Sarah Conell</p>
<p>“The Ethics of Big Data,” <a href="https://www.futurehindsight.com/episode/the-ethics-of-big-data-matthew-l-jones/">Future Hindsight</a> with Mila Atmos</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Teaching</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/teaching.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/teaching.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/3/Screen-Shot-2022-06-21-at-2.25.19-PM.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-06-04T12:15:26-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/3/Screen-Shot-2022-06-21-at-2.25.19-PM.png" alt="" />
                    Princeton Undergraduate Information Revolutions Junior Seminar: Surveillance [Information—Computing—Infrastructure] data: past, present, future (with Chris Wiggins) Computing in Context The Scientific Revolution in Western Europe, 1500-1750 The European Renaissance, 1400-1600 Introduction to Contemporary Civilization in the West Science Across Cultures [Global Core] Civilizing Processes, 1500-1750 Subjects&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/3/Screen-Shot-2022-06-21-at-2.25.19-PM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h3 id="princeton">Princeton</h3>
<h4 id="undergraduate">Undergraduate</h4>
<p><a href="https://registrar.princeton.edu/course-offerings/course-details?courseid=016877&term=1242">Information Revolutions</a></p>
<p><a href="https://registrar.princeton.edu/course-offerings/course-details?courseid=003436&term=1242">Junior Seminar: Surveillance</a></p>
<h4 id="graduate">Graduate</h4>
<p>[Information—Computing—Infrastructure]</p>
<h3 id="columbia">Columbia</h3>
<h4 id="lecture">Lecture</h4>
<p><a href="https://github.com/data-ppf/data-ppf.github.io/wiki/Syllabus">data: past, present, future</a> (with Chris Wiggins) </p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/matthewljones/computingincontext">Computing in Context</a></p>
<p>The Scientific Revolution in Western Europe, 1500-1750</p>
<p>The European Renaissance, 1400-1600</p>
<h4 id="undergraduate-seminar">Undergraduate Seminar</h4>
<p>Introduction to Contemporary Civilization in the West</p>
<p>Science Across Cultures [<a href="http://www.college.columbia.edu/bulletin/core/mc.php">Global Core</a>]</p>
<p>Civilizing Processes, 1500-1750</p>
<p>Subjects and Objects of Renaissance Knowledge</p>
<p>Senior Thesis Seminar</p>
<h4 id="graduate-1">Graduate</h4>
<p>Information—Computing—Infrastructure</p>
<p>Topics in Early Modern European Cultural and Intellectual History: Institutions of Knowledge and Belief</p>
<p>Methods in History of Science</p>
<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ehle7YHZZEe7q6EOhD4T9PMeDnPh-1uE72KSJR3VEEw/edit?usp=sharing">Introduction to Historical Practice in the Age of the Pandemic</a></p>
<p>Introduction to Historical Interpretation and Methods</p>
<p>Topics in Historiography and the Philosophy of History</p>
<p>Foucault for Historians (with Samuel Moyn)</p>
<h4 id="professional-schools">Professional Schools</h4>
<p>Data and databases, with <a href="http://www.decontextualize.com/">Allison Parrish</a>, Columbia Journalism Lede Program</p>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Matthew L. Jones</title>
        <author>
            <name>Matthew L. Jones</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.nescioquid.org/main.html"/>
        <id>https://www.nescioquid.org/main.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/1/1092854966107156481-DyqZhyFUwAAohL1.jpeg" medium="image" />

        <updated>2023-06-04T15:25:57-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/1/1092854966107156481-DyqZhyFUwAAohL1.jpeg" alt="" />
                    history of science, technology, sigint, computing
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.nescioquid.org/media/posts/1/1092854966107156481-DyqZhyFUwAAohL1.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h2 id="history-of-science-technology-sigint-computing">history of science, technology, sigint, computing</h2>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
